Guide to the Steinbeck - Ainsworth Collection
Department of Special Collections
Steinbeck - Ainsworth collection
1880-1992
M1501
Steinbeck, John
Ainsworth, Elizabeth Steinbeck
3 linear feet
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
A collection of materials relating to John Steinbeck, including letters manuscripts, photographs, books, and other materials.
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2005. Accession 2005-274.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection features 65 letters and cards from John Steinbeck to his sister Beth Steinbeck Ainsworth during the 1950s and 1960s, and 10 additional letters written jointly to Ainsworth and another sister, Esther Steinbeck Rodgers. Additional correspondence includes letters from Elaine Steinbeck to Beth, and to Jean Groshong; several letters from John Steinbeck to "Uncle Joe" Hamilton; and other letters among members of the Steinbeck and Hamilton families. Manuscript material includes several short stories composed in the 1920s, and a galley proof of "East of Eden" with at least six minor corrections in John Steinbeck's hand. Other material includes legal documents, photographs, and scrapbook clippings. Individual letters have scope and content notes provided by members of the Wiltshire familiy, descendents of Elizabeth Steinbeck Ainsworth.
Other Finding Aids
Steinbeck (John) Collection, 1902-1979 (M0263) Steinbeck (John). Steinbeck: A Life of Letters: production materials, 1975 (M0354) Steinbeck (John). Wells Fargo Steinbeck Collection, 1892-1981 (M1063)
Container List
- Correspondence, Series 1
  - From Elizabeth Otis to Beth 5/24/1962, letter, typed, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Returning El Gabilan and pictures; typed on McIntosh & Otis notepaper;; location(s): NYC, M&O office
  - From Elizabeth Otis to JS no date, letter, typed, 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Lots of news, then a P.S. - a Mr. Wallace arrived and they agreed on "$3000 a piece"; typed on McIntosh & Otis notepaper; location(s): NYC, M&O office
  - From Beth to Family 1905, 1914, 5 letters, booklet, hand pencil and ink, 23 total p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Beth's letters home from Mills College with Esther; one letter to "Dear Chicken Pox" (John), one to "Brother"; with a 1905 piano recital booklet in which Esther is listed; location(s): Mills College
  - From Beth to Bea and Stanford Steinbeck 2/6/1969, letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Talks of John going to Stockton and being with her during her husband's sickness and death; location(s): Pacific Grove
  - From Beth to Elaine no date, letter, typed, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    After Beth's hip replacement; in response to John and Elaine's request for some addresses; she mentions that it's not easy to understand the Steinbecks; location(s): Pacific Grove(?)
  - From Elaine to Bethie 2/1/1965, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Elaine adds to Beth's coin collection from Ireland; desribes their trip, bad week; news of Harold Guinzberg dying (on previous trip to Dublin); Mary is gone; John got sick; location(s): Ireland(?)
  - From Elaine to Bethie; John Steinbeck Memorial 1/31/1969; February 1970, 2 letters, hand, felt pen (copy), 2 total p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Elaine quotes Robert Louis Stevenson's poem, which Henry Fonda read at John's funeral; location(s): NYC
  - From Elaine to Bethie; Mrs. Riggs 2/25/1975, 2 letters, hand, 4 total p. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Elaine's letter to Beth explaining "Pigasus" (original); second letter from Elaine to Mrs. Riggs with "ad astra per alia parci" (Latin), translated "to the stars on the wings of a pig", or "go as high as you can with the equipment you've got" (copy); location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From Elaine to Bethie - and Liz+Jim 7/24/1989, letter, reviews, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Clippings about Grapes of Wrath play in London; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From Elaine to Bethie no date, letter, hand pencil, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Referring to enclosed Middle Eastern coins for Beth's collection; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From Elaine to Beth no date, letter, hand, ink, 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    John's gall bladder attack (fall of the year of the attack); they're good, getting better; life together; location(s): NYC, 206 E 72nd
  - From Elaine to Bethie no date, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Note about some money John left for Beth, etc.; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From Elaine to Darling (Beth) no date, letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    About spending a day together just prior; after John died; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From Elaine to Beth no date, letter, hand, ink, 5 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    After Gwyn died; the boys making overtures about writing a damning book about John, etc.; possibly 2.5 years after John's death; explaining she shares copies of royalties which have gone into 2nd copyright after John's death; the judgements; threats from the boys; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From Elaine to Dear Ones no date, letter, typed, 17 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Trip to Russia, Poland, Eastern European countries
  - From Elaine to Jean/Bean-bag/Darlink 1969-1975, postcard, 4 letters, hand, ink, 7 total p. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd/Sag Harbor
  - From Elaine to Jean 8/8/1972, letter, hand, ink, 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    With envelope; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From Elaine to Darling One (Jean) 1/6/1975, letter, clippings, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    With envelope; reviews of Broadway revival of Of Mice and Men; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From Elaine to Liz 3/1/1994, letter proof, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Letter with cover of Parini proof; location(s): NYC
  - From Elaine to Steinbeck House Guild(?) no date, letter, hand, ink, 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Appears to be a speech to the Steinbeck House Guild (re: recipe book, John's love of California food); date unknown, but appears to be after 1975; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS to Beth and Gene 8/25/1937, postcard, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Will not stay in Pennsylvania for rehearsals; location(s): Doylestown, PA
  - From JS to Beth 8/5/1951, letter, hand pencil, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Pat Hamilton's death and the end of the Hamilton name; while writing East of Eden; Liz arriving; location(s): Nantucket, MA
  - From JS to Beth 10/16/1952, postcard, hand pencil, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    John working on speeches and Elaine is running "the talent pool" for election in November; location(s): NYC, 206 E 72nd
  - From JS to Beth 5/23/1957, letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    location(s)Rome
  - From JS to Beth no date (1959?), letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    location(s): Somerset
  - From JS to Beth no date (1959?), letter, hand pencil and ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Date sometime while in Somerset; discussion of recent illness; location(s): Somerset
  - From JS to Beth no date (1959?), letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Easter Sunday from Somerset; refers to Mary's illness; rain; US vs. England; location(s): Somerset
  - From JS to Beth no date (1959?), letter, hand, ink, 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Boys with Beth while JS and Elaine are in the UK; lamenting about boys; sending guns to the safe; going home in October; selling house at 206 E 72nd for $90-$100K (bought for $50K) or rent for $600 or $700 per month; seems to be short of money; political references to Stevenson, Averrill, Harriman; location(s): England
  - From JS to Beth Summer 1959, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Boys' studies and time with Beth; location(s): NYC, 206 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Beth 7/1/1959, air letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - From JS to Beth 7/19/59(?), air letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - From JS to Beth and Boys 7/20/1959, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Boys' studies and American kids in general; location(s): Somerset
  - From JS to Beth 8/27/59(?), letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Misc., including itinerary while in the UK; location(s): Somerset
  - From JS to Beth 3/18/1960, letter, hand pencil, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Thom received 1st prize State of Connecticut, 1st prize nationally; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS; Tom to Beth; JS 6/9/1960, 2 letters, typed; hand, ink, 4 total p. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    3 typed pages from John to Beth, 1 in pen from Tom to John (no date); a year after the boys stayed with Beth; laments about Gwyn, the boys, money; mentions Jean's forthcoming baby; his plans to travel the USA in a truck any why; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From JS to Beth 6/22/1960, letter, hand pencil, 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Truck to be delivered in a week; working on Winter of Our Discontent, first line from Richard III; concern for Esther; Holiday magazine buying 25K words of Travels; location(s): NYC or Sag Harbor
  - From JS to Bethie no date (1961?), letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Just after Beth's hip operation; John is 59, has written 26 books; words came to him while awake at 3am...RELAX!
  - From JS to Beth 6/1/1961, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Writes of sending special edition of Winter of Our Discontent to Beth, other copies to Mary and Esther; still working on Charley; going to Sag Harbor. NOTE - he says he means the words in the dedication "To Beth, my sister, whose light burns clear". (Has just turned down an honorary Doctorate of Fine Arts from the University of California.); location(s): NYC, 206 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Beth 7/26/1961, postcard, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    To Beth in Fresno hospital; refers to Beth's hip surgery; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From JS to Beth 7/30/1961, postcard, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    To Beth who was in Fresno Community Hospital, general update; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From JS to Beth 12/7/1961, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Traveling with the boys; concern for Esther at Carroll Rodgers' death; mentions Christmas at the Vatican, midnight mass seats for Pope and choir; location(s): Florence
  - From JS to Beth no date (1962?), letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Talks of speech for Nobel Prize; asking Beth to clean out his mess at 147 11th St. and mentions the safe ("in our garage")
  - From JS to Beth 2/1/1962, letter, hand pencil and ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Boys in northern Italy; Mary off on a tirp; Holiday magazine; location(s): Villa Panorama, Capri
  - From JS to Beth 2/17/1962, letter, hand pencil, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Mary on cruise to Europe; boys to join in a few days; speaks highly of Terrance McNally working with the boys; awaiting news of John Glenn's space trip; more ramblings; location(s): Capri
  - From JS to Beth 2/19/1962, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    location(s): Villa Panorama, Capri
  - From JS to Beth 8/9/1962, letter, hand pencil and ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Ramblings; location(s): NYC, 206 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Beth no date (Fall 1962?), letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Late Nov./early Dec. before accepting the Nobel Prize in 1962; Natalia Lovejoy's address; London, then Sweden Dec. 7-18
  - From JS to Esther and Beth no date (Christmas 1962?), letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Last Christmas in this house; refers to new apartment; location(s): NYC, 206 E 72nd
  - From JS to Beth and Esther 1/2/1963, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Mary's cancer and going to Washington; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Beth 1/31/1963, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Talk of selling the house and moving into an apartment (condo); location(s): NYC, 206 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Beth 3/16/1963, letter, hand, felt pen, 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    More on the problems with the boys, very detailed; location(s): NYC(?)
  - From JS to Beth 5/16/1963, letter, hand pencil, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Death of Charley: John planted willow tree over him, Sag Harbor townspeople planted flowers all around it; dinner with Kennedys, sent copy of Red Pony to their children, Jackie sent a letter which was enclosed, asked to be returned; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Beth Fall 1963, letter, clippings, hand, ink, 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Beth's hip problem; going to Washington, visiting desks in advance of Europe trip, leaving next Mon. or Tues.; seeing Ed Murror tomorrow (old friend); visiting Berlin Wall and Russia (news clip, 12/12/63)
  - From JS to Beth and Esther and Beth(?) 12/2/1963, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Kennedy's death, but proceeding with trip; lots of rumors about his health - all untrue; Sag Harbor house robbed; location(s): Hotel Sacher, Vienna
  - From JS to Beth 1/20/1964, letter, hand, felt pen, 5 p. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Letter meant for Esther and Mary also; full description of problems with Thom and John and then Gwyn; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Beth 1/28/1964, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Beth's typewriter; Gwyn, the boys; weather, etc.; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Beth 2/25/1964, letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Howard Hunter died; want to get Esther to fly east in spring for a couple of weeks; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From JS to All 3/23/1964, letter, typed (dictated), 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Describes going to court with Gwyn; eve of trip to Rome; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS to Beth 5/8/1964, letter, hand pencil, 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Visit from Liz and Jim and mother-in-law; trial next day, suit from Gwyn and the sons; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Mary and Esther and Beth 6/22/1964, letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Boys a bit settled; doing a lot for LBJ and wants to help him get re-elected; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From JS to Beth 10/9/1964, letter, typed, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 61)
    Pat Covici with cancer and ulcer; will ride in "Galway Hunt" at Christmas, Johhny Huston is co-master; losing weight; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS to Beth 10/10/1964, letter, hand, ink, 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Concern for Mary's health; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Bethie 12/7/1964, letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 63)
    Description of flight from San Francisco to Pittsburgh (spelled twice without the "h"); visited kennel for P.B. Floyd (later Angel); Christmas presents - Beth to purchase for Nat Benchley and Robert Wallston; Elaine away taking care of her aunt; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS to Sisters 1/20/1965, letter, hand, felt pen, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 64)
    To US ambassador for inauguration address of LBJ; to Normandy and home in about a week; location(s): Paris
  - From JS to Esther and Beth 1/26/1965, letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 65)
    Death of Mary; location(s): England(?)
  - From JS to Beth 3/12/1965, postcard, hand pencil, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Just received Angel; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS to Bethie 5/19/1965, postcard, typed, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 67)
    Working hard to finish "this book" "before the 30th"; going to Nantucket to stay with Benchleys over anniversary of meeting Elaine, taking Angle who attracts many ticks; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From JS to Esther and Beth no date (August 1965?), letter, typed, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 68)
    Refers to pictures of new pool; "Thom was 21 this month"; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From JS to Esther and Beth 10/23/1965, letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 69)
    Planning trip to England; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS to Beth 11/2/1965, letter, hand pencil and ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 70)
    Refers to Gwyn; writing weekly letters for Long Island paper Newsday
  - From JS to Sisters 11/17/1965, letter, hand, carbon copy, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 71)
    Commissions for Newsday and San Francisco Chronicle
  - From JS to Beth and Esther 1/9/1966, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 72)
    Seeing Mary in the hotel room; travels around Ireland; with envelope; location(s): Waterville, Co. Kerry, Ireland
  - From JS to Beth and Esther 2/13/1966, air letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 73)
    Misc. travels, including Red Sea; location(s): Israel
  - From JS to Bethie 3/29/1966, postcard, typed, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 74)
    Beth's upcoming trip; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS to Bethie no date (Spring 1966?), letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 75)
    Gift to Beth for her trip; no date but before Beth goes to Japan; location(s): Sag Harbor(?)
  - From JS to Bethie 5/28/1966, letter, hand pencil, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 76)
    John going to Vietnam; Beth is in Japan; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From JS to Beth 12/6/1967, postcard, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 77)
    Recuperating
  - From JS to Beth 3/9/1968, postcard, typed, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 78)
    Beth's health; visitors; Thom's orders for Vietnam; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS to Beth 3/23/1968, postcard, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 79)
    Death of Cal; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS to Beth 3/26/1968, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 80)
    With envelope; location(s): NYC
  - From JS to Beth 4/10/1968, letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 81)
    First color TV; dinner that night at a testimonial for Henry Fonda; Pres. Johnson has asked them to the White House for dinner and to stay overnight; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Beth 4/24/1968, letter, typed, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 82)
    Remote control on TV (bought color TV for Beth); going for checkup; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd(?)
  - From JS to Beth no date, postcard, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 83)
    Recuperating; location(s): NYU Medical Center
  - From JS to Beth no date, letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 84)
    One week out of hospital; sent article from magazine "Motorboating"; location(s): NYC, 190 E 72nd
  - From JS to Beth no date, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 85)
    Flying pig at top of page; Beth seeing Jane off; before Mary died; location(s): Sag Harbor(?)
  - From JS to Beth no date, letter, hand pencil, 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 86)
    Refers to John in school
  - From JS to Beth no date, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 87)
    On embossed letterhead; refers to going to New Orleans, following Gwyn there
  - From JS to Bethie no date, letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 88)
    The boys go off to school tomorrow; no clue as to date or location
  - From JS to Beth no date, letter, hand pencil and ink/typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 89)
    Possibly October, after Moscow; talks of the boys, Mrs. Shepherd (her letter enclosed); Mary coming; look for manuscripts which he gives away for tax purposes; location(s): Sag Harbor
  - From JS to Read the card first (Beth?) no date, letter, hand, felt pen, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 90)
    About John - he and a girlfriend took a motor scooter without permission, "she was badly bruised," JS fearing a felony charge; worried enough to put off trip to Pittsburgh to get a dog and a family dinner at the White House with President and Mrs. LBJ
  - From JS to Beth no date, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 91)
    About Beth with new hip in Fresno; unpleasant story about John
  - From JS to Beth no date, letter, hand pencil, 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 92)
    Ramblings; Charley selling well; Pat Covici failing (?); boys off to school
  - From JS to Beth no date, letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 93)
    Something nice an "Ed" said about Beth
  - From JS to Beth no date, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 94)
    Katz; "The Pearl"; post-WWII?; location(s): Cuernavaca, Morelia, Mexico
  - From JS to Beth(?) no date, cablegram, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 95)
    Note from JS; Gwyn trying to reach him; location(s): Moscow
  - From JS to All no date, letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 96)
    Annie Laurie Williams stationary from some hotel room in New York; letter written while Tortilla Flat and another unnamed play were being rehearsed on Broadway; with Carol, planning to leave for Denmark in 2 weeks; before WWII (NYC?)
  - From JS to Joe/Uncle Joe/Joe and Gussie 1939-1940, 3 letters, hand, ink/typed, 6 total p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Discussing the war and JS's potential involvement; motion picture being filmed in Mexico; with envelope dated 5/25/39; location(s): Los Gatos/Mexico City
  - From JS to Joe 10/23/1939, letter, typed (copy), 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Joe is in DC; JS writes of his past writing, has lots of questions about his future; location(s): Los Gatos
  - From JS to Thom and Cal(?) (sons) no date, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    To the boys as they were spending the summer with Beth in Pacific Grove; JS claims he will get off their backs as they get older; location(s): NYC(?)
  - From Clark C. Steinbeck to Cousin Will (Hamilton) no date (1937?), letter, typed, 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Reports of Grosssteinbeck farm; refers to photos; with 2 copies, 6 photos; location(s): Peking, China
  - From Earl Steinbeck to Beth 12/30/1968, 2 letters, typed/hand, ink (copy), 3 total p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Condolences; news about family; with copy of letter JS sent to Earl Steinbeck 1/28/63 while in Sag Harbor; location(s): Burlingame
  - From Joe R. Hamilton to Will, Ollie, George 12/1/1924, letter, typed, 6 p. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Trip to Ireland; family history in Ireland; with 40-50 pages of letters from cousins in Ireland dated 1920s-1930s; location(s): Chicago
  - From Various Hamiltons to Various Hamiltons 1910s-1930s, letters, typed/hand, ink, Many p. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    To, from and about cousins of the Hamilton family in Ireland; location(s): Various
  - From Olive Hamilton (Steinbeck) to Bethie Girl 5/18/2025, letter, hand, ink, 8 p. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    With envelope; location(s): Salinas
  - From Tom Hamilton to Beth 1912, 3 letters, hand, ink/typed, 4 total p. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    location(s): San Francisco
  - From Mary to Beth and Esther 3/30/1962, air letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    On cruise ship Empress of Canada off Mallorca; has sinus infection; writes of her visit with JS and Elaine; writes of JS's health and that he now dislikes crowds and noise; location(s): Palma de Mallorca
  - From E. Tenney(?) to J.A. Steinbeck 11/11/1874, postcard, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Advising that his family started to California this morning (via Worcester, Albany, Buffalo, Chicago and Omaha); location(s): Leominster, MA
  - From Nash Briggs, et al to All the Members of the Order of the Eastern Star 12/19/1883, postcard, typed/hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Stating that John E. Steinbeck is a member of the Order of the Eastern Star; location(s): Hollister
  - From Gwyn to Beth 6/20/1943, letter, hand pencil, 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    John gone; giving Beth requested address; refers to lost baby/miscarraige?; location(s): NYC(?)
  - From Susan F. Riggs, Stanford University to Beth 7/13, 10/4/79, 2 letters, typed, 2 total p. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    To Beth in Pacific Grove; identifies some letter from JS to Kate Beswick; with copies of Stanford Quad photos, summaries of correspondence; location(s): Stanford
  - From Mattie U. Russell, Duke University to Beth 7/3/1974, letter, typed, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Asking Beth for JS materials, etc.; location(s): Durham, NC
  - From Nancy C. Kester to Beth 1/22/1969, letter, hand, ink, 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Note to Beth upon JS's passing
  - From Yevtushenko to Beth 3/20/1979, letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Handwritten tribute to JS, on back of flyer of his two readings at Berkeley and USF; location(s): San Francisco